Albert C. Peale Papers Mss.SMs.Coll.5
American Philosophical Society
- Correspondence, Albert Peale and Family, 1842-1915
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1887 Aug. 11; 1.0 p.
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1887 Aug. 14; 1.0 p.
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1887 Aug. 21; 1.0 p.
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1887 Sept. 4; 1.0 p.
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1887 Sept. 11; 1.0 p.
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1887 Sept. 25; 1.0 p.
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1889 July 21; 2.0 p.
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1889 July 28; 2.0 p.
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1889 Aug. 4; 2.0 p.
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1889 Aug. 11; 4.0 p.
    Scope and Contents note
    Camp 8, Mouth of Jackass Canyon
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1889 Aug. 18; 4.0 p.
    Camp on Bear Creek
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1889 Aug. 27; 2.0 p.
    Camp on Madison River, near Wigwam Creek
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1889 Sept. 8; 2.0 p.
    Madison Valley at Wigwam Creek
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1889 Oct. 5; 1.0 p.
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1890 July 19; 2.0 p.
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1890 Aug. 5; 2.0 p.
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1890 Aug. 10; 2.0 p.
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1890 Aug. 17; 2.0 p.
    Spanish Creek Basin, MT
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1890 Aug. 31; 2.0 p.
    West Fork of Gallatin River
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1890 Oct. 5; 2.0 p.
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1891 Oct. 22; 1.0 p.
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1892 June 21; 2.0 p.
  - Parkers, E. W. to A. C. Peale, 1893 May 26; 1.0 p.
  - Darwin, Charles C. to A. C. Peale, 1893 June 26; 1.0 p.
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1894 Oct. 10; 2.0 p.
  - Peale, A. C. to Charles Richmond, 1894 Nov. 27; 2.0 p.
  - Chesnut, V. K. to A. C. Peale, 1897 Feb. 3; 1.0 p.
  - Blair, H. B. to A. C. Peale, 1900 April 19; 1.0 p.
  - Holmes, J. A. to A. C. Peale, 1904 April 9; 1.0 p.
  - Endlich, G. A. to A. C. Peale, 1905 Nov. 19; 1.0 p.
  - Willard, J. E. to A. C. Peale, 1907 Aug 14; 2.0 p.
  - Smith, Carl D. to A. C. Peale, 1907 Aug 16; 1.0 p.
    Camp Sentinel Butte, ND
  - Lee, W. G. to A. C. Peale, 1908 Dec 7; 1.0 p.
  - Goldman, Marcus I. to A. C. Peale, 1909 March 2; 1.0 p.
  - Unknown to A. C. Peale, Incomplete, 1912 Nov 19.; 1.0 p.
  - Johnson, Mary A. Peale to A. C. Peale, 1912 Dec 22; 8.0 p.
  - Chittenden to A. C. Peale, Year unknown Oct. 21; 3.0 p.
  - Chittenden to A. C. Peale, Date unknown; 1.0 p.
  - Eckfeldt, J.W., M.D. to A. C. Peale, Date unknown; 2.0 p.
  - Eckfeldt, J.W., M.D. to A. C. Peale, Date unknown; 4.0 p.
  - Gannett, Mary C. to A. C. Peale, Year unknown, June 24; 4.0 p.
  - Peale(?), A.C. to E. Wiswell (?), Partial, Date unkown; 4.0 p.
  - Taggart, W. R. to A. C. Peale (?), Date unknown; 2.0 p.
  - Unidentified to A. C. Peale, Date unknown; 1.0 p.
  - Unidentified to A. C. Peale, Date unknown; 2.0 p.
    Camp Carling “In Sioux country”
  - Unidentified to A. C. Peale, Date unknown; 2.0 p.
- Correspondence, Geological, 1878-1946
  - Unidentified to Charles Wachsmuth, 1878 December 10; 2.0 p.
  - Thompson, S. H. to Honorable D. P. Sear, 1879 January 29; 1.0 p.
  - Carpenter, Herbert to Charles Wachsmuth, 1880 September 19; 6.0 p.
  - Carpenter, Herbert to Charles Wachsmuth, 1885 December 10; 8.0 p.
  - Carpenter, Herbert to Charles Wachsmuth, 1886 Jan 9; 8.0 p.
  - Sladen, W. P. to unidentified, 1886 Oct 4; 4.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Charles Wachsmuth, 1887 November 12; 6.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Charles Wachsmuth, 1887 November 21; 4.0 p.
  - Woodward, Henry to Frank Springer, 1888 June 2; 4.0 p.
  - Gregory, Walter to Frank Springer, 1888 October 8; 3.0 p.
  - Fellmer, E. A. and Went, E. C. to E. O. Ulrich, 1888-1893; 45.0 Item(s)
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1900 Oct. 18; 1.0 p.
  - Leman, Waldemar to unidentified, 1901 June 1; 1.0 p.
  - Gregory, Walter to Frank Springer, 1889 February 27; 4.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank (?) to J. W. Kemp, 1902 Aug. 15; 1.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1902 Aug. 15; 1.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1902 Sept. 24; 1.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1903 June 10; 3.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1903 July 12; 3.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1903 Aug 10; 2.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1903 Nov. 28; 3.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1904 March 21; 3.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1904 April 9; 4.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1904 May 1; 4.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1904 May 13; 4.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1904 May 21; 2.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1904 Sept 6; 1.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1904 Sept 14; 1.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1904 Nov. 17; 2.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1904 Nov 27; 1.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1905 April 4; 1.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1905 April 27; 4.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1905 May 17; 4.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1905 May 24; 1.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1905 July 12; 2.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1905 July 18; 1.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1905 Aug 21; 2.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1905 July 12; 1.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1905 Sept 4; 3.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1905 Sept 13; 3.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1905 Oct. 14; 1.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1905 Nov. 17; 1.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1905 Dec 6; 2.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1905 Dec 6; 4.0 p.
  - Bather, F.A. to Edwin Kirk, 1906 March 10; 2.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1906 March 19; 4.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1906 May 5; 4.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1906 June 1; 3.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1906 June 7; 3.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1906 June 10; 1.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1906 June 27; 3.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1906 June 28; 3.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1906 July 9; 1.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1906 July 15; 3.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1906 July 31; 2.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1906 Oct. 28; 2.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1906 Dec. 2; 6.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1907 Feb. 28; 4.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1907 March 6; 4.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1907 March 22; 2.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1907 May 22; 5.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1907 July 1; 4.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1907 August 23; 4.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1907 Oct. 22; 4.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1907 Oct. 28; 1.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1907 Dec 6; 4.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1908 April 11; 1.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1908 May 10; 2.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1908 May 21; 4.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1908 July 9; 2.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1908 Aug 10; 4.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1908 Nov. 5; 3.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1908 Nov. 19; 3.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1908 Dec. 13; 2.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1908 Sept. 1; 3.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1909 March 11; 4.0 p.
  - Springer, Frank to Edwin Kirk, 1909 April 16; 1.0 p.
  - Wilson, H. E. to Mrs. Bassler, 1916 July 12; 2.0 p.
  - Wilson, H. E. to Frank Springer, 1916 September 11; 4.0 p.
  - Harper, John to Dr. Ulrich, 1936 October 14; 2.0 p.
  - Uicolsau, Betty to Edwin Kirk, 1936 May 5; 1.0 p.
  - Kirk, Edwin to Dr. Yang, 1946 August 7; 1.0 p.
  - Kirk, Edwin to C. Y. Lee, 1946 August 8; 1.0 p.
  - Unidentified; List of Instruments for Blowpipe Analysis. Includes prices and chemicals, 1.0 p.
- Peale Family Memorabilia, 1868-1877; Sketch books, receipt (recipe) book, diaries (1868-1877), poetry, correspondences, photographs
  - Berghauser, Kate to Albert (Peale?); Poem, 2.0 p.
  - "C" to "Miss"; Poetry and note to W.J.C., 1.0 p.
  - Calling Cards, various, 8.0 Item(s)
  - Chittenden, J. B. to Holmes, H. H., 1888 (?) August 18; 1.0 p.
    I. O. U.
  - Peale, Rachel Brewer; Lock of Hair
  - Peale, Titian Ramsay; Gunpowder Receipt, 1824 October 19; 1.0 p.
  - Pealite; printed description, 2.0 p.
  - Powell, Samuel photos of seashells, 2.0 Photograph(s)
  - Ulrich, E.O., Photograph
  - Unidentified; Unidentified Man, 1.0 Photograph(s)
    Damaged photo
  - Unidentified; Poetry: "Heroine of Gettysburg" and "Peace for Wednesday April 29", 18?? April 29; 1.0 p.
  - Unidentified; Annotated sketch of Kentucky Warbler, 2.0 p.
  - Unidentified; "Mosquito Story", 2.0 p.
    To be read out by the President (pro term)
  - Unidentified; Poetry, 2.0 p.
  - USGS Envelope, empty
  - Unidentified to Emmie Wiswell, empty envelope, 1870 May 9
  - Unidentified; "50 Passenger Ice Car" annotated postcard, 2.0 p.
  - Wanamaker, John to Mary E. Wiswell, 1891 November 11; 1.0 p.
- Bound Volumes, 1868-1874; n.d.; 12.0 Volume(s)
  - Peale, A.C.; Diary, c. 1865-69; 1.0 Volume(s)
    A.C. Peale, Diary – Philadelphia, c. 1865-69
    Description of a tour of Washington D.C. Details of the trip include the departure from Philadelphia through Wilmington and Baltimore, and tours of major monuments and buildings, including the Patent Office, Government Printing Office, the White House and the Senate Hall. Of particular interest is a short description of a hand shake between Peale and President Johnson during a White House tour.
  - Peale, A.C.; Diary, 1872 May 15 -1872 July 20; 1.0 Volume(s)
    A.C. Peale, Diary, May 15 – July 20,1872
    Documents Mr. Peale’s rail journey from Philadelphia, PA to Omaha, NE where he meets up with the expedition party. The bulk of the diary is Mr. Peale’s description of the activities of the expedition over the course of three months. The party traveled around Western Colorado, Wyoming and Utah. Locations mentioned include: Fort Ellis, Omaha; “The Garden of the Gods” and “Montezuma’s Cathedral.” Also mentioned are the names of various contemporary rail lines. Includes six items originally folded into the back of the volume: Various calling cards and notes.
  - Peale, A.C.; Diary, 1873 May 29 - 1873 August 15; 1.0 Volume(s)
    A.C. Peale, Diary, May 29 - Aug. 15, 1873
    Topics include work in the Cretaceous beds gathering fossils, brief descriptions of canyons, and volcanic peaks, and brief accounts of his ascent of Pike's Peak and Buffalo Peak, and describes difficulties crossing the Platte. Describes encounters with locals such as a German "Dutchman" named Pap, a ranch owner. Expedition members Taggart and Gannett share a camp with several miners at Hamilton who tell of Hamilton's decline from boom times. When the expedition's flour supply dwindles to six pounds, the miners give them 80 more pounds in exchange for some bacon. Near Fair Play on Four Mile Creek, the route of the expedition is changed due to "Indian troubles." On August 8, Peale mentions William Jackson photographing "a beautiful lake which was at the foot of the mountain" at Rock Creek, and Peale comments that "Jackson disturbed us to take a picture." Jackson unfortunately may have lost some of these photographs three days later, when Peale notes that "one of Jackson's mules rolled down and broke a lot of his negatives, so he had to stay behind and take more."
  - Peale, A.C.; Diary, 1873 August 16 - 1873 October 26; 1.0 Volume(s)
    A.C. Peale, Diary, Aug. 16 - Oct. 26, 1873
    Describes the movement of Peale and party between 33 different camps between August and October, 1873, documenting weather problems, supply shopping, travel constraints and rock formations. The last entries describe their departure from Denver to Kansas City upon the Pullman Car.
  - Peale, A.C.; Diary, 1873 May 14 - 1874 July 18; 1.0 Volume(s)
    A.C. Peale, Diary, May 14, 1873 – July 18, 1874
    Records departures from Philadelphia and from camps such as Camp Clear Creek. Includes descriptions of supplies bought for various camps as well as lists of expenditures.
  - Peale, A.C.; Diary, 1874 July 19 -1874 Nov. 10; 1.0 Volume(s)
    A.C. Peale, Diary, July 19 – Nov. 10, 1874
    Documents the expedition along the various branches of the Gunnison River, describing the landscape, the requirements for negotiating the terrain, and the local tribesea. Includes lists of camp numbers and locations and names of pack animals. Contains various loose items: Notes, pressed leaves, and receipts.
  - Peale, A.C.; Diary, 1877 May 27 - 1877 Oct. 9; 1.0 Volume(s)
    A.C. Peale, Diary – Philadelphia, May 27 – Oct. 9, 1877
    Begins with a description of Peale’s journey from Philadelphia to Cheyenne, Wyoming by train, with stops at Chicago, Council Bluffs, Iowa and Omaha Nebraska. It then continues with daily entries recording events at each of the 72 camps made by the expedition, which are also indexed at the back of the volume by date and mileage. ncludes reference to many Indian encounters. For example, on Tuesday June 7, 1877, one of the expedition members met a Shosoni woman who reported that there had been a fight between the whites and the Sioux. In addition, the expedition members saw many lodges of the Bannock along the Snake and Salt Rivers as well as other Indian camps along the ledges of Crow Creek, such as those above the ranch near Smith Fork where one of the boys spoke very good English as noted on June 29. Describes a number of encounters with Shoshoni, such as one in July when almost all of the Shosoni men asked for tobacco. On August 8, Peale reports that two teamsters were killed at the local agency by Bannocks. On the 23rd, he notes that in Montana Gibbon had had a fight with the Indians and lost 300 new guns, ammunition, artillery and commissary stores in Montana.
    Peale also makes note of other travelers that the expedition encounters along the way. For example, on Friday June 15, he sees written on the rocks above the bluff of the Green River the names of “emigrants” (presumable those on their way to California) from 1852 and 1854. He also meets two men on July 15 named Wilson Shippen and Harry Yount who had ascended the highest mountain in the area (unnamed) at 11,000 feet two days earlier, leaving their names on a monument at the summit. He also comments on numerous prospecting and fishing parties, as well as other expeditions being conducted in the area.
    Although Peale has limited contact with the outside world during this expedition, he does note the death of Brigham Young on August 29 and observes that the United State flag was held at half mast on September 2 for his funeral which took place that day.
    Other places mentioned in the journal include: Fremont’s Butte, Landers Road, McDough’s Pass, Oneida Saltworks; gold mines at Caribou below Blackfoot Peak, Fort Hall.
    Other documents tipped in the journal include an invitation from the School of Mines, Columbia College, for a sale of rocks by Alexis Julien, hand-dated June 25, 1877; form collection tags for samples; an admission ticket to the Excusion Ball, signed by John H. Pike.
  - Peale, A.C., Day Book, 1864; 1.0 Volume(s)
    A.C. Peale, Day Book, March 10 – May 18, 1864 Scantily complete day book spanning March 10 - May 18, 1864. Many of the entries focus on the weather for the day. Other descriptions include drills and a very brief mention of the Battle of the Wilderness.
  - Peale, A.C.; Notebook, 1868, undated; 1.0 Volume(s)
    A.C. Peale, Notebook, 1868, n.d.
    Student notes on lectures covering chemistry, hygiene and medicine. Also covered in medical lectures are matters of clothing and marriage. The medical notes are dated April, 1868.
  - Peale, A.C.; Notebook, 1870 May 16 -1870 Nov. 1; 1.0 Volume(s)
    A.C. Peale, Notebook, May 16- Nov. 1, 1870
    Lecture notes taken while Peale was a student at the University of Pennsylvania. Included are lectures on physiology, organic function and gestation. Sketches of lab equipment and of medical charts are also included, as well as drawing and writings on the inside back cover.
  - Peale, A.C.; Sketchbook, undated; 1.0 Volume(s)
    A.C. Peale, Sketchbook, n.d.
    Sketches include landscapes, geometric shapes, garden sites, steam ships, human figures and details of clothing. The book also includes two colored pictures, one of a group of people, seen from behind; and the second of two girls in garden surroundings, also seen from behind.
  - Peale, Harriet; Receipt (Recipe) Book, 1878, undated; 1.0 Volume(s)
    Harriet Peale, Receipt Book, 1878, n.d.
    Mrs. Harriet Peale’s Receipt Book includes handwritten recipes in a lined notebook, indexed in the back by type of dish. In addition, there are numerous recipes, many from different cooks and in different handwriting, including recipes for “Hetty’s Cake,” “Miss White’s Gold and Silver Cake,” and “Mrs. Cooper’s Chocolate Cake.” Also included are printed recipes, such as the small pamphlet entitled “Aunt Matilda’s Selected Receipts and Useful Information,” published in Philadelphia 1878.